Guide to the Joseph Bellamy Papers
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
Joseph Bellamy papers
1752-1785
MS 609
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
0.25
The papers consist of correspondence, sermons and manuscripts of Joseph Bellamy, theologian and minister. In 1738 Bellamy became minister of the new parish of Bethlehem, Connecticut, where he remained until his death. He was a disciple of Jonathan Edwards and a prominent advocate of the New Light theology in the Great Awakening. Correspondents include Jonathan Edwards, John Erskine, Samuel Finley, Samuel Hopkins, John Long, William Smith, and Benjamin Trumbull.
Bellamy, Joseph, 1719-1790
Existence and Location of Copies
Entire collection is also available on microfilm (235 frames on 1 reel, 35mm.) from Manuscripts and Archives, Yale University Library, at cost. Order no. HM4.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of Dr. Harold S. Arnold in 1948 and of Mrs. David Bellamy in 1964.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
The entire collection is available on microfilm. Patrons must use FILM HM 4 instead of the originals.
Scope and Contents
The papers contain twenty-one items of correspondence, sermons, and manuscripts of Joseph Bellamy, theologian and minister of Bethlehem, Connecticut. He was a disciple of Jonathan Edwards and a prominent advocate of the New Light theology in the Great Awakening. Correspondents includeJohnathanEdwards, John Erskine, Samuel Finley, Samuel Hopkins, John Long, William Smith, and Benjamin Trumbull.
The papers came to Yale University in two gifts: from Dr. Harold S. Arnold in 1948 and from Mrs. David Bellamy in 1964. This collection has been filmed. See MICROFILM HM 4.
The researcher should note that the major part of Bellamy's papers is at the Case Memorial Library, Hartford Seminary Foundation, in Hartford, Connecticut.
Great Awakening; Bethlehem (Conn.); United States -- History -- Colonial period, ca. 1600-1775; Sermons; Clergy; Bellamy, Joseph, 1719-1790; Edwards, Jonathan, 1745-1801; Erskine, John, 1721-1803; Finley, Samuel, 1715-1766; Hopkins, Samuel, 1721-1803; Long, John; Smith, William, 1697-1769; Trumbull, Benjamin, 1735-1820
- Inventory
  - Correspondence
    - 1752, 1754-1755 (Box 1, Folder 1, Reel 1U)
    - 1756, 1758-1759, 1763, 1766 (Box 1, Folder 2, Reel 1U)
    - 1768, 1770-1771 (Box 1, Folder 3, Reel 1U)
    - 1783, 1785, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 4, Reel 1U)
  - AMS, sermon, "The Law Our School-Master", 1756 June 8 (Box 1, Folder 5, Reel 1U)
  - Sermons
    - 1741-1755 (Box 1, Folder 6, Reel 1U)
    - 1756-1764 (Box 1, Folder 7, Reel 1U)
    - 1765-1778 (Box 1, Folder 8, Reel 1U)
    - 1779-1798 (Box 1, Folder 9, Reel 1U)
    - n.d. (Box 1, Folder 10, Reel 1U)
  - Unidentified manuscripts, undated (Box 1, Folder 11, Reel 1U)
  - Diploma, 1768 (Box 1, Folder 12, Reel 1U)